<html><tblcnt>0</tblcnt><figcnt>0</figcnt><filefpg>1351</filefpg><filelpg>1353</filelpg><body><div class="WordSection1"><div class="front"><table class="meta" border="1" width="100%"><tbody><tr><td>DOI</td><td class="bookDoi">10.1081/E-ESCS</td></tr><tr><td>Publisher ID</td><td class="bookPubID">E-ESCS</td></tr><tr><td>Article ID</td><td class="bookArtID">120012638</td></tr><tr><td>Book Title</td><td class="bookTitle">Encyclopedia of Surface and Colloid Science, Second Edition</td></tr><tr><td>ISBN - print</td><td class="bookPpub">978-0-8493-9615-1</td></tr><tr><td>ISBN - online</td><td class="bookEpub">978-0-8493-9614-4</td></tr><tr><td>Book Part ID</td><td class="bookPartPubOther">a2638</td></tr></tbody></table><h1 id="tocSeqID1" class="jrnlArtTitle">Composite Materials: Active Filler Interaction with Penetrated Media</h1><p class="jrnlAuthors"><span class="jrnlAuthor"><span class="jrnlGivenName">Oleg L.</span>
 <span class="jrnlSurName">Figovsky</span>
<span rid="AF1" class="jrnlAffRef"></span>
</span>
</p><p id="AF1" class="jrnlAff"><span class="jrnlDepartment">Israeli Research Center</span>
, <span class="jrnlInstitution">Polymate Ltd.</span>
, <span class="jrnlCity">Haifa</span>
, <span class="jrnlCountry">Israel</span>
</p><h1 id="tocSeqID2" class="jrnlAbsHead">Abstract</h1><p class="jrnlAbsPara">Coatings and linings on the bases of chemically resistant polymeric, silicate, and other inorganic nonmetal corrosion-proof materials are widely adopted for the protection of metals, concrete, and structural materials from corrosion in various aggressive media. This brief entry reviews the influence of additives on the operating characteristics of polymeric materials by presenting illustrative examples of key concepts.</p><p class="jrnlKeywordPara">Keywords</p><p class="jrnlKeywordPara"><span class="jrnlKeyword">Composite polymer materials; <span class="jrnlKeyword">Additives</span>
; <span class="jrnlKeyword">Active fillers</span>
; <span class="jrnlKeyword">Penetration</span>
; <span class="jrnlKeyword">Aggressive media</span>
; <span class="jrnlKeyword">Chemical resistance</span>
</span>
</p></div><div class="body"><h1 id="tocSeqID3" class="jrnlHead1">Introduction</h1><p class="jrnlSecPara">Coatings and linings on the bases of chemically resistant polymeric, silicate, and other inorganic nonmetal corrosion-proof materials are widely adopted for the protection of metals, concrete, and structural materials from corrosion in various aggressive media. At present, polymeric mastics, reinforced and film coatings are the most prevalent protective materials for coating and lining of structural materials. In most polymers, chemical destruction takes place in diffuse-kinetic fields, and its rate depends on the penetrability and the stress&ndash;strain state of the coating materials.</p><p class="jrnlSecPara">We were the first to propose the set of inorganic substances of composite polymeric materials which selectively interact with the water or water solutions of acids, salts, and alkalis in order to decrease their penetrability and increase their chemical resistance simultaneously. As a result of the said reactions, high-strength hydrate complexes and inorganic glue cements are formed. As a consequence of this, not only protective features are retained during penetration in aggressive medium but also the coatings become stronger and less penetrable.</p><p class="jrnlSecPara">This is due to the following changes in the protected materials:</p><ul type="bullet"><li><p>In the process of interaction with aggressive medium, hydrate complexes are formed in macropores, microcracks, and other kinds of voids, which are filled up.This process results in &ldquo;repairs&rdquo; of defects and the material is hardened.</p></li><li><p class="">During the formation of hydrate complexes, the volume and contact surface of an active additive expand in the constant volume of the polymeric matrix. This results in the appearance of compressive stress, which compacts the material structure and decreases its free volume. Due to increased specific surface of the filler and formation of a material with binding features, the adhesion on the polymer&ndash;additive boundary becomes higher.</p></li><li><p>The penetrating fluid aggressive medium is used in the upper layers of the coatings to form a new mineral phase and this decreased the rate of medium flux and its sorption by the next layers.</p></li></ul><h1 id="tocSeqID4" class="jrnlHead1">Influence of Additives on the Operating Characteristics of Polymeric Materials</h1><p class="jrnlSecPara">Metal oxides, which are powder-like parts of acid and alkalis glue cements, are suited for such kind of additives. These complexes were investigated and their hardening, strength, and volume characteristics were considered. This allowed to choose purposefully the compositions of the powders to be penetrated into polymeric materials.</p><p class="jrnlSecPara">We investigated the influence of specific inorganic additives on the operating characteristics of polymeric materials after the penetration of the additives into the polymeric matrix. The influence of additives on the diffusion permeability of a polymeric material was evaluated based on the mass change of the samples after exposure in aggressive media, as well as on the penetration depth of the aggressive medium into the polymeric material. The volume-ohmmeter and coulomb-metric methods were used to investigate the modification influence on protective features.</p><p class="jrnlSecPara">For example, the permeability coefficients (<em>&lambda;</em>) and the time of acid penetration through protective layers of low-pressure polyethylene (LPPE) with CaO additives are illustrated in Table <span class="jrnlTblRef">1</span>
.</p><p class="jrnlSecPara">Introducing 3% on mass of the additive Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub>&thinsp;&middot;&thinsp;CuO&thinsp;&middot;&thinsp;CdO in the latex composition &ldquo;Elasticit&rdquo; decreases its permeability into one of the main media for production of mineral fertilizer-hydrate extractive phosphoric acid&mdash;for more than 300 times, while keeping its tensile strength at the same value. By comparison the same latex composition loses 30% of its tensile strength under the same condition if such an additive is not introduced.</p><p class="jrnlSecPara">Electron-microscopic researches and X-ray analysis of the latex surface coating modified by an active oxide fillers after exposure in hydrate-extracted phosphoric acid enabled the detection on the surface a dense film made from hard crystal-hydrates of mixed alumo-phosphates serving as a barrier layer which prevents a deeper penetration of the aggressive medium.</p><p class="jrnlSecPara">The influence of additive modification on the strength characteristics of polymeric materials and the protective features of composition after exposure in aggressive media were studied as well.</p><p class="jrnlSecPara">The analysis of the obtained results allows to state the following:</p><ul type="bullet"><li><p>Inorganic modification additives, which interact selectively with diffusant aggressive media, improve the operating characteristics of the polymeric compositions of all classes, which were investigated.</p></li><li><p>Additives of the said kind not only prevent the decrease in strength characteristics resulting from the exposure of polymer in aggressive medium, but also improve the strength characteristics of polymeric material during the operation. The modification has an influence on the polymeric material both in simple and complex tension conditions (Fig. <span class="jrnlFigRef">1</span>
).</p></li></ul><p class="jrnlSecPara">The dependence of the modifying effect on the content of aggressive inorganic additives is extreme (Fig. <span class="jrnlFigRef">2</span>
). Increase in brittleness of the polymeric matrix results in the narrowing of the optimal field, and the right side of the curve lowers more rapidly. The optimal additive quantity decreases with the decrease in the porosity of the polymeric material. The extremity of this dependence is caused by the formation of aqua-components in the polymeric matrix.</p><p class="jrnlSecPara">The left side of the curve demonstrates the field, where the forming binder fills up the pores of the material. By exceeding the optimal additive quantity, the porosity of the material is not sufficient to compensate for the increase of the additive volume and this results in the appearance of tensions, which cause the destruction of the material, in spite of the further increase in the share of inorganic binding agent.</p><p class="jrnlSecPara">Electronic, microscopic, X-ray, and structural investigations showed that the crystal-hydrates of metals are formed inside the polymeric matrix, but they are different from these, which are formed outside of it. It is caused by the membrane mechanism of mass transit in polymeric materials, as the penetration depth of phosphate and sulfate ions is lower than that of water.</p><p class="jrnlSecPara">By chemical destruction of the polymeric matrix some radicals can be introduced in the aqua-complexes. Therefore, the nature of the effect of additive fillers on the protective features of composite materials is based on the formation of aqua-complexes. Transformation of the active filler into the polymeric matrix is based on the hardening mechanism of inorganic glue cements.</p><p class="jrnlSecPara">In the process of the modified material producing the technological defects appears as a result of thermal tensions in the composition. Introducing the filler increases the share and the size of defects. Locally, near the filler particles, a higher porosity level can be registered. In the process of diffusion of the medium into the polymeric composition, the active filler contacts the acid solution. Therefore, in the hydration process the filler is transformed into an insoluble glue cement which changes significantly the physical and chemical features of the composition. The relative free-space volumes of the matrix (<em>V</em><sup>m</sup>) and the filler (<em>V</em><sup>f</sup>) can be defined as some functions of time (<em>t</em>) and of a medium concentration in the polymer (<em>c</em>), i.e., <span id="M0001" class="jrnlDispFormula" top="9pt" bottom="9pt"> V^{{\rm m}}\,\,=\,\,f_{1}(c,t);\quad V^{{\rm f}}\,\,=\,\,f_{2}(c,t); \fleqno(1)  </span>
</p><p class="jrnlSecPara">The transforming rate of the filler into cementing glue depends on the rate of chemical reaction (<em>V</em><sub>x</sub>) and mass transfer (<em>V</em><sub>m</sub>). This process can occur in kinetic or diffuse fields. If the diffuse field takes place, i.e., <em>V</em><sub>m</sub>&thinsp;&x226A;&thinsp;<em>V</em><sub>x</sub>, the transformation stage depends on the quantity of fluid penetrating in this point of the composition during the time (<em>t</em>). When the rate of chemical reaction is significantly slower than the rate of diffusion, <em>V</em><sub>x</sub>&thinsp;&x226A;&thinsp;<em>V</em><sub>m</sub>, the transformation stage of the active filler into a glue-cement can be described as <span id="M0002" class="jrnlDispFormula" top="10pt" bottom="9pt"> V^{{\rm m}}\,\,=\,\,V_{0}^{\rm f} {\rm e}^{-kct} \fleqno(2)  </span>
where <em>k</em> is the efficient constant of the rate of chemical reaction depending on the concentration of water solution in the fluid and <em>V</em><sup>f</sup><sub>0</sub> is the initial relative free-space volume of the filler.</p><p class="jrnlSecPara">In the process of the transformation, the active filler increases the initial absolute volume and this results in the appearance of local compressing tension in the polymeric matrix and partial filling up of material defects.</p><p class="jrnlSecPara">The diffusion process, where the diffusion coefficient depends on the medium concentration and time and is accompanied with mass absorption, can be described in cylindrical coordinates as follows: <span id="M0003" class="jrnlDispFormula" top="9pt" bottom="9pt"> {\rm \partial}c / {\rm \partial} t\,\,=\,\,(1/r)({\rm \partial} / {\rm \partial} r)[D\cdot r ({\rm \partial} c / {\rm \partial} r)] \,\,-\,\, q \fleqno(3)  </span>
where <em>D</em> is the diffusion coefficient, <em>q</em> is the volumetric absorption intensity of the aggressive medium due to the chemical reaction, and <em>r</em> is the current radius of the hollow cylindrical sample.</p><p class="jrnlSecPara">The diffusion coefficient in quasi-stationary conditions (d<em>c</em>/d<em>t</em>&thinsp;=&thinsp;0) is<span class="jrnlBibRef" data-citation-string=" 1 "><sup>[1]</sup></span>
<span id="M0004" class="jrnlDispFormula" top="8pt" bottom="8pt"> D\,\,=\,\,{\rm \partial} \theta / {\rm \partial} t [\ln(r_{\rm out} \,\,-\,\, r_{\rm inn})/2\pi l(c_{\rm inn} \,\,-\,\, c_{\rm out})] \fleqno(4)  </span>
where &part;<em>&theta;</em>/&part;<em>t</em> is the velocity of the acid solution flow, <em>r</em><sub>out</sub>, <em>c</em><sub>out</sub> and <em>r</em><sub>inn</sub>, <em>c</em><sub>inn</sub> are, respectively, the radiuses and saturation concentrations of outer and inner surfaces of the hollow cylindrical sample with length l.</p><p class="jrnlSecPara">Investigation of the protective mechanism of composite materials with additives, which selectively interact with aggressive media, as well as the influence of modifying additives, provides hint on choosing the modifying additives taking into account the kind of composite polymeric materials and their operating conditions.</p><p class="jrnlSecPara">The modifying additive should form with an aggressive medium influencing the polymeric material a high strength glue-cement. Introduction of ions, which were formed as a result of the destruction of the polymeric matrix, as well as the interaction of the forming glue composition, is also expedient. The most optimal case is when the concentration of an aggressive medium is slightly higher than the optimal concentration of the medium of the glue-cement forming.</p><p class="jrnlSecPara">In case of significant differences between the concentrations of aggressive media influencing the modified polymeric material and optimal concentrations of the same media that dictate quantities of the modifying additives, it is advisable to introduce a complex additive designed to have optimal concentration for a given media, i.e., those designed for both higher and lower concentrations of the aggressive medium influencing the polymeric material.</p><p class="jrnlSecPara">The amount of the modifying additive should be chosen based on the criterion that an increment of the inorganic component volume must be equal to or slightly higher than that of the pores&rsquo; volume of the polymeric composition in the process of chemical interaction and hydration.</p></div><div class="back"><h1 id="tocSeqID5" class="jrnlRefHead">Reference</h1><p id="CIT0001" class="jrnlRefText"><span class="RefSlNo">1.</span>
 <span class="RefAuthor"><span class="RefSurName">Figovsky</span>
, <span class="RefGivenNames">O.</span>
</span>
 <span class="RefBookTitle">Improvement of Protective Properties of Polymeric Materials</span>
; <span class="RefPublisherLoc">Moscow</span>
, <span class="RefYear">1990</span>
.</p></div></div></body></html><div class="jrnlTblBlock"><p id="T1" class="jrnlTblCaption"><span class="label">Table 1</span>
<span class="caption">Influence of calcium oxide on the diffusion parameters of LLPE</span>
</p><table border="1" width="100%"><colspec align="char" char="." colname="col7" colnum="7" colsep="0" rowsep="0"></colspec><colspec align="char" char="." colname="col6" colnum="6" colsep="0" rowsep="0"></colspec><colspec align="char" char="." colname="col5" colnum="5" colsep="0" rowsep="0"></colspec><colspec align="char" char="." colname="col4" colnum="4" colsep="0" rowsep="0"></colspec><colspec align="char" char="." colname="col3" colnum="3" colsep="0" rowsep="0"></colspec><colspec align="char" colname="col2" colnum="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0"></colspec><colspec align="left" colname="col1" colnum="1" colsep="0" rowsep="0"></colspec><thead><tr><th align="left"></th><th></th><th></th><th colspan="3">Time of acid penetration for unfilled <strong><em>t</em></strong><sub>0</sub> and filled polymer matrix <strong><em>t</em></strong><sup>f</sup><sub>0</sub></th><th></th></tr><tr><th align="left" rowspan="2">Aggressive medium at 70&deg;C</th><th rowspan="2">Amount of CaO (parts by weight)</th><th rowspan="2"><strong>&lambda;</strong>(<strong>&mu;</strong>m/hr)</th><th colspan="3">Thickness of LLPE layers (mm)</th><th></th></tr><tr><th align="center">1</th><th class="tborder">3</th><th>5</th><th><strong><em>t</em></strong><sub>0</sub>/<strong><em>t</em></strong><sup>f</sup><sub>0</sub></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>20% HCl</td><td>0</td><td>125</td><td>65</td><td>595</td><td>1,623</td><td>&mdash;</td></tr><tr class="tborder"><td> </td><td>1</td><td>41</td><td>596</td><td>5,355</td><td>14,875</td><td>9.1</td></tr><tr class="tborder"><td> </td><td>5</td><td>21</td><td>2,265</td><td>20,400</td><td>56,650</td><td>34.8</td></tr><tr><td>30% HF</td><td>0</td><td>60</td><td>62</td><td>2,340</td><td>6,500</td><td>&mdash;</td></tr><tr class="tborder"><td> </td><td>1</td><td>50</td><td>50</td><td>3,600</td><td>10,000</td><td>1.5</td></tr><tr class="tborder"><td> </td><td>5</td><td>33</td><td>33</td><td>8,280</td><td>23,000</td><td>3.5</td></tr></tbody></table></div><div class="jrnlFigBlock"><p id="F1" class="jrnlFigCaption"><span class="label">Fig. 1</span>
<span class="caption">Destruction curves for flat stress state: A&mdash;samples before exposure in the aggressive medium; B&mdash;samples with an active filler after exposure in 30% solution of SO<sub>4</sub> during 500&thinsp;hr; and C&mdash;the same samples as in B but without additive.</span>
<img class="jrnlFigures" src="jobs/tandf/ESCS3_Batch1_B08/E-ESCS-120012638/Fig/f0001.gif" alt="f0001.gif"></p></div><div class="jrnlFigBlock"><p id="F2" class="jrnlFigCaption"><span class="label">Fig. 2</span>
<span class="caption">Dependence of tensile strength index of modified ebonite compound on the modification component content after exposure in 10% solution of HNO<sub>3</sub> during 1 year.</span>
<img class="jrnlFigures" src="jobs/tandf/ESCS3_Batch1_B08/E-ESCS-120012638/Fig/f0002.gif" alt="f0002.gif"></p></div>